In this video we'll setup
このレッスンでは、シーンの
the collisions for our scene.
衝突を設定します
Let's start by zooming out our scene view.
まず Scene ビューをズームアウトしてはじめましょう
I'm going to do this by scrolling the mouse wheel
マウスのホイールをスクロールして
to bring the entire background in to view.
ビューにバックグラウンド全体が入るようにします
Right now our background image
現在、バックグラウンド画像は
shows a visual representation of walls.
見た目には壁の表示になっています
But as we'll have noticed,
ただし、お気づきの通り
these walls do not actually prevent
実際には、壁はプレイヤーの通過を
the player from moving through them.
妨げていません
They're simply artwork on a 2D sprite.
それらは、単なる 2D スプライトの図柄にすぎません
They don't affect the mechanics of the game
見えているだけで
beyond giving us something to look at.
ゲームのメカニックに影響しません
In order for the Player game object
Player ゲームオブジェクトや
or any other physics object to be
その他の物理オブジェクトが
obstructed by the walls we'll need to add
壁に妨害されるためには、
collider components to the game object
壁を表現しているゲームオブジェクトに
to represent these walls.
コライダーコンポーネントを追加する必要があります。
A collider is a shape or
コライダーは形状か体積で
volume which is used by the physics engine
衝突を識別するために
to identify collisions.
物理エンジンに使用されます
The physics engine detects collisions
物理エンジンは、シーンの
between two or more colliders in the scene.
複数のコライダーの間の衝突を検知します
For the physics engine to identify the
物理エンジンが衝突を識別するには
collision at least one of the
衝突するゲームオブジェクトのうち
colliding game objects
最低 1 つに
must have a rigidbody2D component.
rigidbody2D コンポーネントの設定が必要です
As we discussed before, in this project
以前説明した通り、このプロジェクトでは
we're using 2D physics.
2D の物理演算を用いています
And so we'll be using the collider2D component.
そのため、Collider 2D コンポーネントを使用します
The collider2D component defines
Collider 2D コンポーネントは
a 2D shape, or line, which the
2D の形状や線を定義します
2D physics engine will use
それらを使って、2D 物理エンジンは
to calculate collisions.
衝突を計算します
In this project we'll place 2D colliders
このプロジェクトでは、プレイフィールドの4 角に
around the edge of the play field
2D コライダーを置き
to keep our Player game object from
Player ゲームオブジェクトが
leaving the game.
ゲームから飛び出ないようにします
We'll also add a collider to the Player
Player にもコライダーを加え
so that the 2D physics engine can
2D 物理エンジンが
detect collisions with the environment.
環境との衝突を検知できるようにします
Let's highlight the Player game object.
Player ゲームオブジェクトをハイライトします
The Player game object already has
Player ゲームオブジェクトにはすでに
a rigidbody2D component attached.
rigidbody2D コンポーネントがアタッチされているので
So we don't need to add another.
これ以上 rigidbody2D を加えることは不要です
This will allow the Player game object to
これだけで Player ゲームオブジェクトは
participate in collisions as
衝突に含まれます
it will meet the requirement of
なぜなら、衝突を検知するための
having at least one game object
rigidbody2D をアタッチしたゲームオブジェクトを
with a rigidbody2D attached
最低 1 つ持つという条件が
in order to detect collisions.
満たされているからです
First let's add a 2D collider to our Player.
最初に 2D コライダーを Player に加えます
The Player is circular in shape,
この Player は円形なので
so we'll use a circle collider 2d component.
Circle Collider 2D コンポーネントを使用します
With the Player still highlighted
Player をハイライトしている状態で
click the Add Component button.
Add Component ボタンをクリックします
If we type Circle
Circle と入力すると
the circle collider 2D will appear.
Circle Collider 2D  が表示されます
Select that and add it to the Player.
それを選択し Player に加えます
With the collider added let's focus in on the Player.
コライダーを加えたところで Player に注目しましょう
Place your mouse over the scene area
シーンにマウスオーバーし
and with the Player selected press the F key.
Player を選択したままF キーを押します
When we add a collider it's
コライダーを加えると
automatically scaled to match
自動的にスプライトのサイズに
the size of the sprite.
合わせてスケールします
In this case this leaves us with
この場合 UFO の周りに
some empty space around our UFO.
隙間が残っています
We can modify this by changing the
これを修正するには
collider's radius.
コライダーの半径を変更します
Let's set the radius so that it
半径を設定すれば
more or less matches the shape of the sprite.
多少、スプライトに一致するようになります
By clicking and dragging on the
Radius フィールドのラベルを
title of the Radius field
クリック & ドラッグすると値が変化します
we can see that a value of 2.15 works pretty nicely.
値2.15 でぴったり合うようです
Now let's add colliders
今度は、壁に
to our walls.
コライダーを加えましょう
Let's highlight the background.
Background をハイライトします
Mouse over the scene.
シーンにマウスオーバーし
And push F to frame selected.
F キーを押してフレームを選択し
And we'll use the mouse wheel to zoom it in.
マウスホイールを使ってズームインします
With the Background object selected
Background オブジェクトが選択された状態で
let's choose Add Component
Add Component
Physics 2D
Physics 2D
Box Collider 2D.
Box Collider 2D の順に選択します
In the scene view we'll notice
Scene ビューの
that a green box has appeared
Background スプライトの境界に
around the borders of our background sprite.
緑の囲いが現れます
Let's play the scene to test.
では、シーンをテストしてみましょう
As we can see,
ご覧のように
the Player flies up to the
プレイヤーは画面の最上部まで
top of the screen.
飛んで行ってしまいます
The reason this is happening is because
この理由は、ゲームをスタートしたとき
when we start our game the physics engine
1 つの 2D 空間に
determines that we have two objects
2 つのオブジェクトがあると
occupying the same 2D space.
物理エンジンが判定したからです
The Player is inside the box
プレイヤーがバックグラウンドの
collider for the background.
ボックスコライダーの中にあります
The physics engine's solution
物理エンジンは
is to push the two objects apart
アタッチされたすべてのrigidbody2D に力を加え
by adding forces to any
2 つのオブジェクトを引き離して
attached rigidbody2Ds.
解決しようとしました
Because the Player is the only game object
ゲームオブジェクトの中で
with a rigidbody2D attached
rigidbody2D がアタッチしているのは
it's the only game object that will have
Player だけだったので
forces applied to it,
プレイヤーだけに力が作用し
and it goes flying out of the way.
外に押しやられました
The issue here is that our physics
現段階の問題点は
system currently thinks our background
Background オブジェクトは1 つの固体オブジェクトで
object is a single solid object,
Player も固体オブジェクトであるため
and that the Player, also a single solid object,
Player は Background の中にあるべきではないと
shouldn't be in the middle of it.
物理システムが考えていることです。
To fix this we're going to replace
解決策として、壁を表している
our single large collider
1 つの大きなコライダーを
with a set of smaller colliders.
複数の小さいコライダーに
to represent the walls.
取り換えることにします
To make the colliders easier to see
コライダーが見やすいように
we can temporarily switch the
Scene ビューウィンドウの左上の
scene view from Shaded Mode
Draw Mode メニューを使って
to Wire Frame Mode
Shaded モードから Wireframe モードに
using the Draw Mode menu
一時的にScene ビューを
in the upper-left of the scene view window.
切り替えます
Now we can see just the
これで、スプライトのテクスチャに
underlying shapes of the objects in our scene
紛らわされることなしに
without the distraction of the texture
シーンのオブジェクトの形だけを
of our sprites.
見られるようになりました
The game object can have multiple
ゲームオブジェクトに
colliders attached to it, and we're going to
複数のコライダーをアタッチできるという特性を
take advantage of this for our game.
このゲームに利用できます
Currently we have one collider 2D component.
現在、1 つのCollider 2D コンポーネントがあります
Let's move it in to a better position
もう 1 つ加える前に、もっと良い場所に
before we add another one.
これを移動しましょう
Each collider has it's own properties.
各コライダーは独自のプロパティーを持っています
We're going to use the Offset
Box Collider 2D の
and Size properties of our box collider 2D
Offset と Size プロパティーを使用して
to scale and position our collider
コライダーのスケールと位置付けを行い
to have it act as a wall.
壁のように動作させます
First let's set our collider's
まず、Size プロパティーを使用して
shape using the Size properties.
コライダーを設定しましょう
By default Unity attempts
Unity はデフォルトで
to fit the size of the collider
コライダーのサイズを、アタッチしている
to the size of the sprite it's attached to.
スプライトのサイズに合わせようとします
This means that one dimension
つまり、四角形の 1 つの辺は
of our square is already correct.
すでに正しくできているということです。
Let's keep the value for the Y axis
Y 座標の値はそのままにしておいて
and adjust the value for X.
X の値を調整しましょう
We'll start by setting the X size to 3.3
X のサイズを 3.3 に設定しましょう
Let's switch the scene view back
Scene ビューを元に戻して
to shaded mode.
Shaded モードにします
Now we have a shape that's
位置は正しくないけれど
reasonably wall-like but in the wrong position.
まあまあ壁のように見える形ができました。
We'll use the Offset X property
Offset の X プロパティーを使用し
to move our first collider over
コライダーを右に移動します
This can be done either by clicking
これを行うには
and dragging on the title of the
X のフィールドのラベル上で
X axis field or by entering
クリック & ドラッグするか
the value numerically.
数字を入力します
Let's set the x Offset
Offset X を 14.3 に
to 14.3
設定しましょう
We now have one wall,
壁が 1 つできました
but we need three more.
あと 3 つ必要です
Let's duplicate our first collider
最初に作ったコライダーを複製し
to create the opposing wall.
反対側の壁を作成します
Using the component context menu
コンポーネントの右上の
in the upper-right of the component
コンテクストメニューで
choose Copy Component.
Copy Component を選びます
Afterwards click the same menu again
その後、同じメニューを選んで
and choose Paste Component As New.
Paste Component As New を選択します
This will paste a new copy of
これで、同じ設定のコンポーネントの
the component with the same settings.
新しいコピーを貼り付けます
Now we're going to reverse the position
今度は
of the box collider 2D along
Offset X　を -14.3 に設定して
the X axis by setting
Box Collider 2Dを
the X Offset to -14.3
X 軸に沿って反対側に置きます
Next we'll use the same process
次に、同じ要領で
to create our upper and lower walls.
上方と下方の壁を作成します
Choose Paste Component As New again
Paste Component As New を再度選択し
to create a third copy of our
Box Collider 2D の
box collider 2D.
3 つ目のコピーを作成します
Now we're going to move it in to position
X と Y を入れ替えることによって
by swapping the X and Y values.
その壁を正しい位置に移動します
Set the Y Size to 3.3
Size Y を 3.3 に
and X to 31.64
Size X を 31.64 に設定します
Now set the X Offset to 0
Offset X を 0
and the Y Offset to 14.3
Offset Y を 14.3 に設定します
Now using the component context menu
コンポーネントのコンテクストメニューを使用し
let's copy the component values of the third collider
3 番目のコライダーのコンポーネントの値をコピーし
and Paste Component As New
Paste Component As New を実行し
to create the fourth wall.
4 つめの壁を作ります
We'll set the Y Offset to be -14.3
Offset Y を -14.3 に設定し
and we're done.
完了です
Let's enter play mode to test.
テストするには、プレイモードにします
Now the Player will collide with all
プレイヤーは4 つの壁すべてに衝突し
four walls and stay within the play field.
プレイヤーフィールドにとどまります
It's worth noting the although the
加えたボックスコライダーが
box colliders we added overlap each other,
互いにオーバーラップしても
they won't create a collision or go flying
衝突したり飛んで行ったりすることはありません
because they don't have a rigidbody2D
rigidbody2D がアタッチしていないので
component attached and therefore
他方から力の作用を
won't receive forces from one another.
受けないためです
It's fairly common for colliders
静的な動かないオブジェクトを使って
to overlap each other in this manner
平面をレイアウトするとき
when laying out levels
コライダーがこのように互いに
using static non-moving objects.
重複するのは一般的です
In our next video we'll get our
次のビデオではカメラを動かして
camera moving and following the Player.
プレイヤーを追跡します